Guide to the Judy Malloy Papers, 1956-2010
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Early Artists Books, 1976-1990, (3 boxes)
  - Artist Book statements, 1984-1987 and undated (Box 11)
    Includes 1984 statement about Malloy's work with a price list of works; "Photographic Artist's Books" statement from July 10, 1987; undated handwritten early notes about computer-mediated books.
  - Untitled artists book (with Day Use Permit case) (Box 26)
  - Bumps on the Chips, 1980 (Box 26)
  - Up, 1975 (Box 26)
- Writings and Programming, 1968-2012, (6 boxes)
  Includes a small amount of material on Malloy's paper-based written works, but the majority of this series relates to Malloy's electronic works, hyperfiction, and computer programming.
  The disks containing Malloy's works have been removed from the collection to be individually transferred to Duke's Electronic Records Server. This includes early versions of Uncle Roger, the Apple II versions of Uncle Roger, drafts of its name was Penelope, IBM disks of Yellow Bowl and Molasses, a final version of Wasting Time, the software version and Eastgate releases of its name was Penelope, the Eastgate version of Forward Anywhere, Thirty Minutes in the Late Afternoon and You!. Please contact a reference archivist for this material.
  - Authoring software, Eastgate Systems: Storyspace and Storyspace tools (disks removed) (Box 13)
  - Interactive Art Conference on Art Wire interviews, 1995-1996 (Box 25)
  - Essays and Books
    - The Arts on the Internet: Art, Advocacy, News, and Information, Center for Digital Democracy, 2004 (Box 3)
      Essay by Malloy and resources used by her in the essay. Originally published on CDD website.
    - "Reading From the Screen, Four Writers at Hypertext '04," Tekka 2:4 (2005) (Box 3)
      Draft of article and related email correspondence.
    - Women, Art & Technology materials, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      Book reviews, material from a Cyberfem Panel that Malloy hosted in 1999, and material about the exhibit The Tipping Point: Health Narratives from the South End, by artists Jen Hall and Blyth Hazen.
    - Arts Wire; Arts Wire Current; NYFA Current: An Online Arts Presence, 1992-2004 consultant's report, 2004 (Box 25)
    - Sonya Rapoport materials (Box 25)
      Related materials from Malloy's work on Pairing of Polarities: The Life and Art of Sonya Rapoport, 2012 Includes interviews, notebooks, brochure, and essay.
    - Reconstructing Uncle Roger draft, 2012 (Box 25)
    - "Authoring Systems," in Johns Hopkins Guide to Digital Media and Textuality, 2013 (Box 25)
    - Malloy's online recollections, 2011-2013 (Box 25)
  - Unpublished writings, (1 folder)
    Includes early children's book manuscript, poems, and songs.
    - Tom Barley and the Battle of Dogtown, 1968 (Box 12)
    - Poems: "The Frog Dog King Thing," "The Snake Cake Chicken," "The Cat Bat Kitchen Table" (Box 12)
    - Songs written for Malloy's son and his classmates in Oakland (Box 12)
  - Bad Thad, 1980, (1 folder)
    Bad Thad is a children's book by Judy Malloy, published in 1980 by E.P. Dutton with illustrations by Martha Alexander.
    - Correspondence with E.P. Dutton, 1977-1981 (Box 12)
    - Folded sheets of the book (Box 12)
    - Press materials and reviews (Box 12)
    - Bad Thad, 1980 (Box 12)
  - The TV Blew Up, 1980
    Card catalog poem made from 50 3x5 photos, drawings, and text and filed in a plexiglass box; it can be read sequentially or hypertextually. The work was shown in Technical Information, SITE, San Francisco, CA, March 3-28, 1981 (partially funded by the NEA), and Hearst Strip, Location/Dislocation, Berkeley Art Center, Berkeley, CA, April 25-May 23, 1980.
    - Complete work (Box 18)
  - OK Genetic Engineering, 1983-1985, (1 folder)
    This information art project looked at the social implications of genetic engineering.
    - Project summary, records, photos, project layouts, and correspondence (Box 12)
    - "OK Research, OK Genetic Engineering, Bad Information: Information Art Describes Technology," written by Malloy (Leonardo 21:4, pages 371-375, 1988) (Box 12)
    - Research, correspondence, and artwork from the project, (3 folders) (Box 27)
  - I don't care if I never get back, ca. 1985
    Sequential photo-poem meant to be used in Radio Shack's battery-operated address books that electro-mechanically moved a roll of paper on which you could write addresses. Malloy made several artist books by replacing this paper with a roll of sequential photos; this project consisted of photos taken of people in the bleachers at Oakland A's games.
    - Mockup of "tape" (Box 18)
  - Bad Information, 1986-1988, (3 folders)
    For this project, one of the first pieces of online collaborative information art, Malloy invited participants to help create a satirical database. The searchable database that this produced concerned the impact of computers on society and the tendency not to question computer-produced information. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/badinfo/bad.html.
    - Bad Information, ACEN version, 1987 (disk removed) (Box 12)
    - Search Requests, 1987 (Box 12)
      For this project, an offline database was created with excerpts from computer magazines and documentation. Cards were physically sent to various participants, who were invited to return the card labeled with a keyword they had selected from a provided list. Malloy then printed out the results of the search for that keyword and sent it to the requester. The notebook contains the search requests Malloy received.
    - Keywords in the Bad Information Base and keyword search for "Robots" (Box 12)
  - Uncle Roger
    Uncle Roger was begun online on Art Com Electronic Network (ACEN) on the WELL on December 1, 1986. It was first told as an online serial with the keywords provided in each lexia-based installment, so that the readers could create their own version of the work using their own database software.
    The work consists of three parts: File 1, A Party in Woodside; File 2, The Blue Notebook; and File 3, Terminals.
    A working hypertextual version was published online (programmed with UNIX Shell Scripts) on ACEN from 1987-1988 with each part appearing separately. The publication of File 2 was partially funded by the California Arts Council and Art Matters. At the same time, 1987-1988, disk versions of this work were self-published and distributed by Art Com -- first Apple II and then IBM PC. The disk version was also included in the traveling exhibition, Art Com Software, as well as in other exhibitions.
    Uncle Roger was first adapted for the World Wide Web in 1995 and revised in 2003. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/uncleroger/unclerog.html. The best overall reference for Uncle Roger is Judy Malloy, Uncle Roger, An Online Narrabase, in the journal issue Connectivity: Art and Interactive Telecommunications, Leonardo 24:2, 1991 (which is included in the Printed Materials series).
    - Topic 14: A Party in Woodside, as first told on WELL, 1986 December (Box 3)
    - A Party in Woodside, UNIX programs and documentation, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - A Party in Woodside, Apple II version written in BASIC, 1987 (Box 3)
    - ACEN menus, undated (Box 3)
    - The Blue Notebook, BBS version on ACEN on the WELL, 1987 (Box 3)
    - The Blue Notebook, ACEN and UNIX programs and documentation, 1987 (Box 3)
    - The Blue Notebook, original ACEN text (2 representative samples), 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - The Blue Notebook, ACEN text, 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - The Blue Notebook, Apple II+ version, written in BASIC, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Terminals, initial proposals (unrealized), 1988 (Box 3)
    - Terminals, ACEN version (Box 3)
    - Terminals, stand alone copy (disk removed) (Box 3)
    - Pre-copyedited version, 1991 (Box 3)
    - PC version, programs in BASIC, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Art Com correspondence and feedback, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Art Com distribution, contract and catalog (Apple II), 1988 (Box 3)
    - Art Com software, Digital Concepts and Expressions, 1988 November (Box 3)
    - Packaging, disk components (Box 3)
    - Packaging, disk versions, Apple II (disks removed) (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions, 1987-1989, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Articles mentioning Uncle Roger, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
    - Web version printout, 1995 and 2003 (Box 3)
    - Printout of "A Party in Woodside," 2003 (Box 3)
    - Reviews and interviews, 2012 (Box 25)
  - its name was Penelope
    Its name was Penelope was created by Malloy in three different versions, with additional variations in the first two versions. The Exhibition version dates from 1988-1989. The Artists Software version was published by Malloy's Narrabase Press in 1990, and was distributed by Art Com. Finally, the Eastgate version began publishing in 1993.
    - Background readings on structure and programming, 1972-1979 and undated (Box 3)
    - Artists notebook, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Exhibition version documentation, 1989 and undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibition version packaging, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Exhibition version, 1989 (disk removed) (Box 3)
      This is the version used for the Richmond Art Center Exhibition.
    - Programs, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Software, 1990 (disks removed) (Box 3)
    - Narrabase version publicity, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Eastgate version press and publicity, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
    - Notes for the Eastgate version, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Eastgate disks and correspondence, 1992 (disks removed) (Box 3)
    - Software, 1993 (disks removed) (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions, 1989-2008 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1990-1993, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Final edits, introductions, reviews, and correspondence, 1993 and undated (Box 3)
    - Reviews (Box 25)
  - Molasses, 1988, (2 folders)
    Malloy was invited to create this work in the offices of The Whole Earth Review using a Mac, HyperCard, and an Apple computer. She used the cards (drawings, photographs, and texts) from one of her card catalogs (HOME) and also created the audio for the work. It was exhibited at the Art Com Software Show along with Uncle Roger. She published it via Bad Information (Berkeley, CA) in 1988.
    - Xeroxes of screens, Art Com Software Show, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Sound notes, Art Com Software Show, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Thirty Minutes in the Late Afternoon, 1990, (1 folder)
    Thirty Minutes in the Late Afternoon was a collaborative work created on ACEN on The WELL in 1990. It was conceived and produced by Judy Malloy and written by Malloy in conjunction with Anna Couey, Abbe Don, J. Matisse Enzer, Carole Gould, ISAST, Eleanor Kent, Carl Loeffler, Tom Mandel, Gil MinaMora, Harold Poskanzer, Howard Rheingold, The Normals, Fred Truck, and Kathleen Watkins. The actions and words of three characters were written on a conferencing system, divided into four topics which were then formatted into three columns by Malloy. The work takes place October 17, 1989, the date of the Loma Prieta earthquake; most of the writers would have been in the Bay Area at that time.
    - "Thirty Minutes in the Late Afternoon," guest editorial by Malloy in ArtCom Magazine, October 1990 (Box 12)
    - First page of a version of the paper, probably published in Networker (Box 12)
    - Entire work (printout included, disk removed) (Box 12)
    - Printouts of some of the topics where the work was written (Box 12)
    - Writer permissions (Box 12)
  - You!, (2 folders)
    You! was a collaborative narrative data structure, created in 1991. Exhibitions include Reflux, at the Sao Paulo Biennial in Brazil (1991), as well as INTERNET, in New York City (1995). It was also included on the CD that accompanied The New Media Reader, edited by Noah Wardrip-Fruin and Nick Montfort (2003). It is available on the web at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/you/index.html
    - Packaging materials, printouts, and statements, 1991 (disk removed) (Box 4)
    - Exhibition version, text instructions, 1992 (disk removed) (Box 4)
  - Brown House Kitchen, (1 folder)
    Created in LambdaMoo while working for XEROX PARC. The creation is documented in Malloy's article Narrative Structures in LambdaMOO, in In Search of Innovation: the XEROX PARC PAIR Experiment, edited by Craig Harris, 2000.
    - Documentation, 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - Wasting Time, (4 folders)
    A narrative data structure published in After the Book: Writing Literature Writing Technology, Perforations 1:3, Spring-Summer, 1992, guest edited by Richard Gess.
    Other disks removed from this subseries include Stuart Moulthrop's Dreamtime and Shawn Fitzgerald's Yet Still More. These floppy disks were originally from Perforations' After the Book.
    - Instructions and packaging, 1991 (disk removed) (Box 4)
    - Perforations 1:3, Spring-Summer 1992 (some pages and all disks are missing) (Box 4)
    - Jane Douglas, "Gaps, Maps and Perceptions," 1992 (Box 4)
      From Perforations.
    - Program printout, 1992 June (Box 4)
    - Editor material, instructions, etc., 1992 (Box 4)
  - XEROX PARC, 1991-1999, (3 folders)
    Articles, speech notecards, and other materials from Malloy's time as an Artist-in-Residence.
    - Contract, other materials, 1995 and undated (Box 4)
    - Speech notecards, undated (Box 4)
      Draft of a speech given at XEROX PARC as part of a Computer Science Laboratory called Dealer.
    - Articles about XEROX PARC, 1991-1999 (Box 4)
  - Making Art Online, 1993-1994, (3 folders)
    Work of information art that was one of the first art works available on the World Wide Web. Originally hosted by CSIR's Anima website. A version is now on the Walker Art Center website.
    - Printout from Walker Art Center website, 2010 (Box 4)
    - FineArt Forum, 1991 and 2002 (Box 25)
      2002 Disk from Fine Art Forum's 15th anniversary has been removed for preservation.
  - The Yellow Bowl, 1993-1995, (2 folders and 1 box)
    The Yellow Bowl was exhibited at Interactive Art, FISEA, in Minneapolis, Minn., November 1993, and also at Digital Identities, Sheppard Gallery, at the University of Nevada in 1995. Although the work was under contract to Eastgate in 1994, it was never published, largely due to Malloy's accident.
    - Most of the text and BASIC program, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Grace's notes (Box 18)
      Handwritten texts on fragments of watercolor paper and enclosed in a box labeled with information about the installation; written as a draft notebook for The Yellow Bowl and then used in an installation at DIGITAL IDENTITIES: Technologies of Meaning, Sheppard Gallery, University of Nevada, Reno, February 3-March 3, 1995.
  - l0ve0ne, 1994, (2 folders)
    According to Malloy, l0ve0ne is one of the fist officially published new media literature on the web.
    - Draft version of text (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with Polish translator (Box 4)
    - Reviews, 2001 and 2004 (Box 25)
  - Forward Anywhere, 1995-1996, (3 folders)
    Forward Anywhere was cowritten by Malloy and Cathy Marshall. After installations at The ADA Show, Artemesia Gallery, Chicago, March 1996 and the Xerox PARC 25th Anniversary, Xerox PARC Corporate Lobby, Palo Alto, CA, September 1995, it was published in Wired Women, ed. Cherny and Weise, 1996, p. 56-70. The installations featured a laptop with the actual work that was placed on an informal garden table to simulate Malloy and Cathy Marshall's meetings to plan this work; the table also held notebooks, containing emails exchanged by Malloy and Marshall.
    - Forward Anywhere galley proof, 1995 (disk removed) (Box 4)
    - Eastgate flyer, Wired Women materials (Box 4)
    - Notebooks used in installations of Forward Anywhere, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - The Roar of Destiny, 1996-1999, (2 folders)
    File includes printouts of Unix directory that includes all the files that comprise The Roar. Also contains articles about the piece, dating 1998-1999, and early versions. The authorized edition is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/roarofdestiny/control.html.
    - Unfinished and undated versions (disks removed) (Box 4)
    - Directory printouts and articles (Box 4)
  - Dorothy Abrona McCrae, 2000, (2 folders)
    This work is a hyper-epic about an 81-year-old Bay Area Figurative painter. Malloy wrote it in 2000 and revised it in 2008. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/dorothy_abrona_mccrae/.
    - Complete text (Box 12)
      Includes a statement about the work, a list of the approximately 800 files that comprise the work, a coding chart for the beginning of the work, and notes for part 4 of the work.
    - Information used in the writing of various "Dorothy" stories (Box 12)
      Includes postcards, pamphlets, brochures, file key charts, and photos.
    - Reviews (Box 25)
  - A Party at Silver Beach, 2002, (1 folder)
    This work of electronic fiction takes place at a party. It follows Dorothy Abrona McCrae, precedes Afterwards, and is narrated by Jenny Clark, the narrator of Uncle Roger. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/weddingparty/begin.html.
    - Printouts of most of the pages (Box 13)
  - Afterwards, 2003, (1 folder)
    Afterwards chronicles the relationships of three couples, one of which is Dorothy and Sid (from the Dorothy stories). It immediately follows A Party at Silver Beach. It was published by the Iowa Review Web, from which it is available at http://iowareview.uiowa.edu/TIRW/TIRW_Archive/tirweb/feature/malloy/index.html, and is mirrored at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/dorothyandsid/begin.html.
    - Correspondence with the Iowa Review Web (Box 13)
    - Printouts from the Iowa Review Web and Malloy's website (Box 13)
  - Art California Web, 2004-2012
    In parternship with the California Studies Association, Malloy produces and hosts this web portal intended to provide greater online access to California artists and art organizations.
    - Information and top pages, 2005-2006 (Box 22)
    - Notebooks, 2005-2006 (Box 22)
  - Concerto for Narrative Data, 2005-2008, (1 folder)
    This work of hyperpoetry, which could also be performed, has six artist and writer narrators, including Dorothy and Sid from the Dorothy stories, and concerns covert surveillance. It was published in the Iowa Review Web in 2008 and was featured in the Centenary of Carmen Conde in Spain in 2007); the 2006 FLEFF Film Festival in Ithaca, NY; and The Rose Goldsen Archive of New Media Art at Cornell. It is available at http://iowareview.uiowa.edu/TIRW/vol9n2/artworks/concerto/begin.html.
    - Correspondence with various editors and curators (Box 13)
    - List of files (Box 13)
    - Early version - top pages (Box 13)
  - The Wedding Celebration of Gunter and Gwen, 2006-2007, (1 folder)
    This is a magical realist text opera which was featured in featured in Visionary Landscapes, the 2008 Electronic Literature Organization International Conference Exhibition. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/celebration/begin_celebration.html.
    - Correspondence about the work's exhibition at Visionary Landscapes (Box 13)
    - Printout of the final arioso (Box 13)
  - Paths of Memory and Painting, 2010, (3 folders)
    This trilogy is part of the Dorothy stories. Part I, where every luminous landscape, is a work of new media poetry which was shortlisted for the Prix poesie-media 2009 (Biennale Internationale des poetes en Val de Marne) and featured at The Future of Writing (UC Irvine, 2008), Cover to Cover (KPFA Radio, Berkeley, 2008), and the E-Poetry Festival (Barcelona, 2009); Part II, when the foreground and the background merged, is an interlude of three recollected scenes; and Part III, paths of memory and painting, is a closing text-based trio sonata. All are available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/luminous_landscape/paths.html.
    - "where every luminous landscape" (Box 13)
      Printouts and correspondence with curators
    - "when the foreground and the background merged" (Box 13)
      Printouts and drafts
    - "paths of memory and painting" (Box 13)
      Text and documentation
    - Painted notebook from Paths of Memory and Painting, undated (Box 26)
  - From Ireland with Letters, 2012
    This work of hyperfiction, which premiered at Malloy's retrospective at the 2012 Electronic Literature Organization Conference at West Virginia University, concerns Irish people who were sold as slaves in America in the 17th century. It is available at http://www.well.com/user/jmalloy/from_Ireland/begin_from_Ireland.html.
    - Preliminary chart for the prologue (Box 13)
    - Notes, notebooks, chart, and first piece of the musical score (Box 25)
- Exhibitions, 1970s-2000, (4 boxes)
  Includes exhibitions, installations, and performances of Malloy's artists books, cartoon narratives, and new media.
  - Artists Books (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970s (Box 4)
    - Word Works, San Jose, Calif., 1976-1979 (Box 4)
    - Artwords and Bookworks, Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Wiggly Bush Meadow, exhibition, San Francisco Public Library, April 18-May 27, 1978 (Box 4)
      With Doyle Saylor; sponsored by La Mamelle, Inc. As part of the LOCATION project; partially funded by the National Endowment for the Arts.
    - 3x5, Visual Card Catalogs, exhibition, Artworks, Venice, Calif., September 18-October 18, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Mail Art Shows, 1979-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Location/Dislocation, installation, Berkeley Arts Center, Berkeley, Calif., April 25-May 23, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Franklin Furnace, 1981-1986 (Box 4)
    - Technical Information, installation, SITE, San Francisco, Calif., March 3-28, 1981 (Box 4)
      Partially funded by National Endowment for the Arts.
    - Bound to Be, exhibition, Catskill Gallery, Catskill, New York, April 17-May 12, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Books as Art, exhibition, Eaton/Shoen Gallery, San Francisco, Calif., June 14-July 25, 1981 (Box 4)
      Curated by Franklin Furnace. Show also traveled to University of Arizona Museum of Art, University of New Mexico Museum of Art, the Walker Museum, and others.
    - Judy Malloy: Recollection, installation, Heller Gallery, University of California at Berkeley, March 1-27, 1982 (Box 4)
      Ideas in this work were later used in Malloy's new media literature, such as its name was Penelope.
    - Bookworks, exhibition, National Library of Madrid, Madrid, Spain, September 15-October 15, 1982 (Box 4)
    - Bookworks: 1982, exhibition, Moore College of Art, Philadelphia, Penn., October 1982 (Box 4)
    - Experimental Books, exhibition, Texas Women's University, Denton, Texas, November 8-December 5, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Xerox Annual, exhibition, Intersection Gallery, San Francisco, Calif., December 1983 (Box 4)
    - Books Artists Have Made, exhibition, Cleveland Institute of Art, Cleveland, Ohio, February 17-March 2, 1984 (Box 4)
    - I Never Get Jealous, Pauley Ballroom, University of California, Berkeley, Calif., October 30, 1984 (Box 4)
    - San Francisco Art Institute, 1984-1989 (Box 4)
      Many annual exhibitions and events.
    - Handmade Photographic Books, exhibition, National Society for Photographic Education Conference, Minneapolis, Minn., March 14-17, 1985 (Box 4)
    - Photographic Books, exhibition, Allen Street Gallery, Center for Visual Communication, Dallas, Texas, May 13-16, 1985 (Box 4)
    - The Book in Time, exhibition, SUNY Purchase, Purchase, New York, October 1985 (Box 4)
    - Photographic Handmade Books, exhibition, Texas Women's University, Denton, Texas, January 1986 (Box 4)
    - Experimental Books, exhibition, Works, San Jose, Calif., October 1986 (Box 4)
    - Bookworks, exhibition, A.N. Bush Gallery, Salem, Oregon, May 28-June 28, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Monumental Women, installation, SOMAR Gallery Space, San Francisco, Calif., September 18-October 31, 1987 (Box 4)
    - Books Without Bounds, exhibition, Irvine Fine Arts Center, Calif., December 4, 1997-January 14, 1988 (Box 4)